this is an ABC color
[Music]
presentation Walt Disney's Disneyland
When You Wish Upon a
Star makes no difference who who you
are each week as you enter this Timeless
Land one of these many worlds will open
to
you Frontier
land tall tales and true from the
legendary
[Music]
past tomorrow land promise of things to
come Adventure Land the Wonder World of
Nature's Own
realm Fantasy Land the happiest Kingdom
of them
all presenting this
[Music]
week many years ago a prophetic writer
and engineer
told of the genius of one man who
discovered the very power of the
universe and harnessed it to propel his
ship 20,000 Leagues Under the
Sea but the hero of that story was
afraid to let this power fall into the
hands of an immature
Mankind and so he chose rather to
destroy his own work
[Music]
yet there is
hope in God's good time Nature's Own
energies will come to
humankind for a
better and a richer life
fiction often has a way of becoming fact
not long ago we brought you the immortal
tale 20,000 Leagues Under the Sea
featuring the famous submarine
Nautilus according to the story this
craft was powered by a magic force today
that tale has come
true this is a model of the real
Nautilus the world's first Adam powered
ship it's the first example of the
useful power of the atom that will drive
the machines of our atomic age the atom
is our
future it is a subject everyone wants to
understand so we felt it was the most
important topic for a Tomorrowland
program in fact we considered it so
important that we embarked on several
Atomic projects for one we made plans to
build an exhibit of Disneyland
that will show you atomic energy in
action now our Atomic projects here at
the studio are two-fold we prepared this
program and also a book so that we could
tell you this important story in full
detail both grew together we gave them
the same title and many of the
illustrations appear in both as you can
see we found ourselves deep in the field
of nuclear physics
of course we don't pretend to be
scientists we're storytellers so we
combine the tools of our trade with the
knowledge of experts we added a
nationally known scientist to our staff
to head our new science
department his first assignment was to
write the book on the adom and to help
us in developing this program and here
to tell you the story of our friend the
Adam is the author of our book Dr heimes
hobber as we developed our story of the
atom we made an amazing Discovery we had
a science story but suddenly we realized
that it was almost like a fairy tale by
a strange coincidence our story turned
out to be like the old Fable from the
Arabian Knights the fisherman and the
genie this tale tells of an age-old wish
of man a wish to be the master of a
mighty Genie that does his
bidding there was once an fisherman who
lived in great
poverty one day after casting his net
many times he happened to pull ashore a
prisen
vessel its mouth was closed with a l
stopper marveling at his strange catch
the fisherman said I'll wager that
whatever is sealed so well must contain
something of great are
[Music]
you Lord that presently thou wil have to
die heaven forbid or at least tell me
why As I Lay imprisoned in that tiny jar
for many centuries
my anger grew and grew until I swore in
my heart that my Liberator should perish
what a cruel trick fate hath dealt
me
trick
H oh Genie since Thou Art determined
upon my death grant me this one last
question
well how can one as mighty and Powerful
as thou dwell in so tiny a vessel what
thou Dost not believe me not till I have
seen it done can I believe
it watch
then now you shall return to the Sea N N
I did not mean what I said no release me
and I give my solemn vow to Grant the
three wishes
[Music]
strangely enough our story is like that
Fable come true through signs we are
like the
fishermen for centuries we have been
casting our net into the sea of the
great unknown in sech of knowledge and
finally we found a vessel and like the
one in the Fable it contains a genie a
genie hidden in the atoms of this metal
uranium let me show
you this is a giga counter it tells us
that the genie is here impr present in
these atoms
so this is our story how the vessel was
discovered how the genie was
liated how he first threatened to kill
and how he was finally harnessed to
crant us three
wishes Our Story
begins in ancient Greece in 400
BC at that time man firmly believed that
all things were composed of four basic
elements
earth air water and
fire but democratus a philosopher of
that era thought that these elements
could be divided into smaller particles
in fact he even gave them their name
atomos which means
indivisible I crumbled this Earth to
soil and in turn crumbled this soil to
dust now if I could could reduce this
dust into its smallest
particles these would be
atoms this beach appears to be a solid
carpet but on closer inspection we see
that it is made of millions of grains of
sand if we think of grains of sand as
atoms and pack them together they can be
molded into any desired form so it is in
this way nature uses these tiny
particles these atoms to build all
things the earth water air and
fire if air and fire consist of small
particles how can they
rise they would fall to the Earth like a
shower of
Pebbles the man who disagreed with
democratus was Aristotle a famous Greek
philosopher
his philosophy shaped the thinking of
man for the next 2,000 years and so the
idea of the atom was
lost in the 17th century man went beyond
mere thinking he began to act his
philosophy became seeing is
believing he invented the telescope and
this magic instrument greatly extended
his range of
sight he saw mountains and craters on
the face of the
Moon he found that the planet Venus also
showed faces just like our
moon and that Jupiter has moons of its
own he saw For the First Time The
reddish disc of Mars
and the Beautiful rings of
Saturn with a telescope man discovered
the universe in all its unbelievable
richness at about the same time a second
powerful instrument was invented the
microscope it opened up an entirely new
and Tiny World for for man to
explore it was a world full of strange
patterns and Designs man found them in
ordinary things such as
[Music]
wood and the feathers of
birds in the bodies of
insects and in the scales of
fish the microscope revealed infinite
details in everything
there was hidden Beauty in miniature
seashells so tiny that millions of them
form only a whsp of
powder even a single drop of pond water
revealed forms of life never before
seen tiny one- celled animals and
plants the microscope gave man his first
look into Nature's miniature Universe a
world teeming with fantastic forms of
life with a microscope man also
discovered the beautiful and regular
forms of
[Music]
crystals he marveled at the delicate
shapes of
snowflakes in thousands no two are
alike in the regular shapes of crystals
lay hidden the secret of the atom's
existence of course the microscope
doesn't show atoms they are much too
small for that but it made man aware
that everything he saw and discovered
must be composed of something still
smaller one of the first men to explore
Nature's tiny realm was John Dalton an
English chemist this was early in the
19th century
it was he who revived the idea of the
atom I believe democratus was right all
things are made of
atoms take copper for
instance my drawings show how the atoms
group
together they are like little hard
indestructible
balls with some unknown force acting
between
them when the atoms pack together
layer upon layer Millions upon
Millions then they build a tiny
Crystal and when the crystals combine
they form the copper metal we are so
familiar
[Music]
with and there are also atoms for Silver
and Gold
there are different kinds of atoms
everywhere atoms for sulfur in a
match atoms for carbon in every ordinary
pencil atoms for mercury in a
thermometer a different kind of atom for
each element but most of Nature's
Creations are
mixtures this glass is a mixture of
different kinds of
atoms the wood here
another this book is composed of more
mixtures than I could name the secret of
how nature creates her mixtures was
first understood in 1811 through the
work of amadio avagadro of
Italy when atoms of different elements
combine they form into small compact
masses which I call
molecules I have found that there is a
different proportion of atoms for each
kind of molecule for examp example when
one atom of oxygen combines with two
atoms of hydrogen they form the most
common molecule in nature this of course
is H2O
water it takes billions and billions of
these water molecules to make a single
drop of water
they are so tiny that they cannot be
seen even through the most powerful
microscope
however the microscope does reveal an
important fact about atoms and
molecules it shows that they are in
constant motion these are dust particles
in a drop of water and you can see that
they are being kicked around by the ever
busy water
molecules it was over a 100 years ago
that an early microscope first revealed
that atoms and molecules are constantly
on the
Move now in a flame for example the
motion of the atoms and molecules is
extremely violent and this is why a
flame is hot our skin is equipped with
tiny organs that can feel this violent
movement as
heat or even
pain now in this glass the molecules are
moving much more slowly and and so it
feels normal to the
touch even in an ice cube the molecules
are moving but very slowly and this is
why the ice feels
cold let's look at heat with an atomic
eye so to speak atoms of course don't
burn up they merely rearrange themselves
forming molecules of soot and
Ashes so that you can see what is going
on on we will accurate the size of the
atoms over a billion
times the molecules in the flame Dash
around with great speed and bounce
against the molecules of the class they
transfer their violent motion to the
class and finally to the
ice it's like a pool game with the balls
bouncing against each
other if more heat is applied the ice
molecules will move faster and faster
and finally break loose lose from each
other the ice
melts as the movement becomes more
violent the water begins to
boil the molecules are kicked away from
the surface as
Steam in hot steam they're dashing
around with great force enough Force to
bounce the lid of the jar
[Music]
there is power in steam power that can
do more than just lift a
lift when this force was put to use it
ushered in the mechanical age
[Music]
it was the power of steam that turned
our generators to produce electric power
and the gas light era then became the
age of electricity
true steam was a mighty servant but it
was a hungry
servant it had to be fat constantly and
satisfying its hunger cut deep into our
precious resources of coal and
oil man had not yet found the genie of
our
story in fact he hadn't even found the
vessel in which the genie was
[Music]
imprisoned the year was
1896 again in search of knowledge the
net was cast into the sea of the unknown
and like in our
Fable a catch was made an accidental
catch the discovery was made by AI beel
a French
scientist today I discovered something
very
strange I happened to leave a piece of
uranium on a wrapped photographic plate
in a dark drawer when I developed the
plate I found that it was fogged
apparently the uranium had exposed it
even in the darkness and through the
rapid this uranium it seems to possess
some mysterious activity and give off
some type of radiation
all by
itself set
extraordinaire beel had discovered
radioactivity Pierre and Marie C two
other French scientists were greatly
intrigued by this strange
phenomenon while seeking the source of
the radiations from uranium they
discovered a new element which gave off
even stronger
rays look our new
element how radiant it is it even glows
in the
dark we should call it
radium radium turned out to be a
mysterious source of
energy this remarkable element would go
on radiating like an endlessly flowing
spring this was against all laws of
science known at that
time how could this tiny Mass contain so
much
energy this mystery shook the very
foundations of
[Music]
science it was finally understood in
1905 when Albert Einstein discovered an
important new law his theory showed that
every Mass contains a tremendous amount
of
energy e stands for
energy M for
mass and c² is the speed of light
multiplied by
itself now C squ is a very great
number and so if multiplied by even a
small Mass the result will be a very
great amount of
energy this is a cold scientific
explanation but its deep meaning can be
easily understood through our Fable
Einstein like the fishermen found that a
mighty force was contained in a small
vessel radium constantly releases tiny
bits of its energy through radiation a
little bit every
second and there is so much energy that
this activity can go on for thousands of
years these rays were actually tiny
fragments of atoms breaking
apart no longer could the atom be
considered the smallest particle in
nature evidently the atom was not an
indestructible little ball after
all but then what was
it the first clue to this question came
from Lord Ernest Rutherford of England
the year was
1911 today I used the fast flying
fragments of radium as tools to probe
into the
atom I placed a small sample of radium
inside a solid lead block
the lead absorbed all the Rays except
those that were allowed to escape
through a small opening in the
block one might say it was a sort of
atomic
gun to make the ray bullets visible I
used a fluorescent
screen for a Target I chose a very thin
Leaf of
gold but to my surprise the bullets from
my Atomic gun passed right through the
gold leaf as though it wasn't there it
was like like shooting at a
ghost this was truly amazing because the
gold leaf was a solid wall 2,000 atoms
thick so the atom can't be as solid as
we always
thought then
unexpectedly one out of thousands of
bullets ricocheted striking something
solid
[Music]
I can only conclude then the atom is
mostly empty space like a cloud or
shell but occasionally I hit something
solid it must be very
small a tiny particle in the center
I shall call
it the nucleus of the
atom with RF for's discovery of the
nucleus scientists began to understand
how nature builds her
atoms the shell of the atom appears
solid just as a fast whirling fan seems
solid actually the shell is composed of
a whirling swarm of tiny electrical
particles called
electrons they circle around the nucleus
like planets around the Sun so the atom
is like a tiny solar
system but scientists are ever
curious like the fishermen who examined
the vessel he had hauled ashore they
began to probe the atomic nucleus for
its secrets
[Music]
they found that it was composed of small
particles electrically
charged they called them
protons which means primary
particles later to the great surprise of
science other strange particles were
discovered in the
nucleus they had no electrical charge
they were neutral and so they were
called neutrons
at last The Mystery of the atom
structure was
solved how amazing nature is think of it
there are countless solar systems of
atomic Suns and planets in everything
there's a whole universe in the tip of a
pencil even in this tiny pencil dot
there are billions of times more atoms
than there are people on our
Earth there are many kinds of
atoms it's interesting to see how they
differ in the various elements it's a
fascinating study in numbers let's start
with number one the simplest atom in
nature one proton and one electron give
us the element hydrogen a very light
gas nature always keeps an electrical
balance in her atoms so if the nucleus
has two protons it will also have two
circling electrons
this makes an atom of
helium there are also neutrons in the
nucleus that add to its weight and so by
simple addition nature builds the atoms
of all her
elements six protons and six electrons
and some neutrons for
[Music]
carbon six 15 and 16 for
sulfur 26
a 47
silver
79 gold
[Music]
92 uranium the famous radioactive
element here Nature has crowded so many
protons and neutrons into the nucleus
that it becomes
unstable finally it throws out a small
fragment and and in this way radioactive
rays are
born these Rays cannot be seen heard or
felt the Giga counter is used to detect
their
presence it gives off audible clicks
when the race pass through
it and there there is another instrument
which even makes the race visible to the
naked
eye this special device is called a
Cloud
chamber it contains a tiny bit of radium
which gives off a constant shower of
atomic
fragments of course the fragments
themselves are much too small to be seen
but you can now see their
Trails each new vapor trail shows that
another atom has thrown off a fragment
each atom does this only once in its
entire life but there are so many atoms
that this activity is going on almost
[Music]
endlessly we might say that a
radioactive atom is like a set mous
strap both contain
energy the traps on this table represent
the atoms in a piece of
radium every so often one breaks down
all by itself releasing a bit of
energy but radium is useless as a power
source there aren't enough atoms
releasing the energy at the same
time but nature knows all the secrets of
the atom since the beginning of time she
has used atomic energy to power the
whole universe and to light the fires in
the
sky the best example is our own Sun
these are actual time-lapse pictures of
the sun's
Rim that vast display of energy comes
from an atomic fire raging deep in the
core of the
Sun if this was an ordinary fire the sun
would burn to a dead heap of Ashes
within a few thousand years
but so much energy is produced by these
atoms that the sun will go on Shining
for billions of years to
[Music]
come for a long time alone knew how to
open the vessel that contained this
Mighty
Force to man however the vessel remained
closed finally he discovered the secret
of how to open the vessel
himself the fisherman used his knife and
Man Too found a tool that broke the
seal the year was 1938
the place Berlin
Germany the leading character that
strange metal called
uranium again it turned out to be the
star of a sensational scientific
discovery OT and frit strasman were
probing the secrets of the uranium atom
like raford they used Atomic
bullets they used neutrons the neutral
particles that were discovered hidden in
the nucleus of the
atom the neutron is an ideal
bullet since it is neutral it isn't
deflected by the electrical charge of
the atoms and flies through them in a
straight course
finally it struck a
nucleus the uranium nucleus split in
two Atomic fishion had been
accomplished but this wasn't all that
happened two neutrons were released from
the split
[Music]
nucleus one bullet was used to split the
atom and two new ones were created in
the process
now we have two neutrons to split two
atoms this implied a fabulous Prospect a
nuclear chain reaction in
uranium let's go back to our mous strap
atoms we can create a chain reaction
with
them we'll use our two ping pong balls
for
neutrons they will be
released when the atom
splits now all all these Mouse straps
are the atoms that will be in the
game they are set loaded and ready to go
to start the Chain Reaction all we need
is one
Neutron it has to trigger just one trap
the ping pong balls that are released
will set off two other traps and then
we'll have four balls flying to trigger
more traps I think you can see what is
going to happen watch
an atomic Chain Reaction Works in
exactly the same way one Neutron is
enough to start it
[Music]
the atomic Genie was
freed and his devastating Force posed a
fearful threat
[Music]
the world was deeply shocked by the
first atomic
explosion we all wondered if atomic
energy had better remained a secret
forever we are like the fisherman when
he first beheld the frightful form of
the genie he too wished that he had
never found the
vessel no that presently thou wil have
to die heaven forbid but our Fable had a
happy
ending the fisherman had his means of
making a friend of his
enemy and fortunately science has its
way of doing the same thing an atomic
blast is more than a threat it is also a
regretful waste of heat and
radiation to make this energy useful the
explosion must be slowed
down let me show you what I mean our
Mouse trrap explosion can be slowed down
with the aid of a slow motion camera
[Applause]
as you can see the chain reaction is now
spread over a longer period of time the
energy is released slowly and the Heat
and radiation stay within useful
limits Atomic scientists produce slow
nuclear chain reactions within the
famous Atomic
reactor it's really just a furnace with
thick concrete walls to encase the
atomic
fire blocks of uranium serve as atomic
[Music]
fuel to slow down the Chain Reaction
control rods that absorb neutrons are
inserted in the
blocks these rods act like a damper in
the furnace and catch some of the flying
neutrons and take them out of
play this allows fewer atoms to split
and keeps the reactor burning almost
endlessly at an even
temperature with the Chain Reaction thus
under control the mighty atom can be put
to
use the heat is picked up by a liquid
that is piped through the hot core of
the
reactor the heated liquid is then run
through a boiler where it produces an
almost endless stream of hot steam Steam
for
power but there's more than heat the
atomic reactor has the magic power to
make many ordinary materials
radioactive if for example a piece of
ion is exposed to the shower of neutrons
inside a reactor the ion atoms pick up
extra neutrons and become Radioactive
[Music]
in this way the reactor creates for us
artificial radioactivity in many
elements like natural radium they are
valuable Tools in science and
medicine the atomic reactor then gives
us a chance to make the atomic Genie our
friend he will come forth to our
beckoning and just as in the Fable he
will grant us three
wishes the decision is ours what should
we wish for what do we need
most our coal and oil will not last
forever yet we need ever more power
so for the growth of our
civilization our first wish shall be for
power
here with my right hand I give you the
magic fire of the
atom it is
yours the atomic fire is an almost
endless source of
heat we can use it in power stations for
producing
electricity electric power of our modern
civilization
[Music]
and then the atom will run our
ships and of course the atomic submarine
already
exists the atomic fire can heat air as
well as
water then the atom becomes the driving
force of a Chet
engine it can drive an
[Music]
airplane an airplane that circles the
world many times without ever Landing
for
fuel and eventually the atom will help
us to cast off the shackles of gravity
and fly through the fast reaches of
outer
space here we are burning up our Co and
oil only to produce
power but now we have a new source of
power clean silent plentiful colon oil
can now be saved for better things we
can use them for making Plastics dyes
textiles and drugs
mankind has ever suffered from hunger
and
disease so our second wish shall be for
food and
health with this hand I give you a
source of beneficial
Rays they are magic tools for research
that will help you to create food and to
cure
diseases magic tools indeed they are
these radioactive
race for example an ordinary needle can
be made
radioactive and then if it is hidden in
the proverbial hay stack it can easily
be found by the Rays it gives
[Music]
off like this needle all radioactive
materials can be traced by their
Telltale
Rays with radioactive chemicals we can
now literally watch how plants grow and
we can trace plant nourishments from
soil to
fruit in this way science will help to
produce bigger and richer
[Music]
crops the growth of animals can be
studied in the same way and the best
food can be found for better and
healthier livestock
so the atom creates more food for our
ever growing
population and these same rays are the
tools of atomic
medicine radioactive sodium for example
is used for timing the flow of blood
through the living human
body it is injected into the arm and
then a gigaa will record how long it
takes to reach the
heart this is a great help in
recognizing heart
[Music]
conditions in diseases of the thyroid
gland radioactive iodine performs an
amazing
job if mixed in an atomic cocktail it
will gather in a thyroid because iodine
is attracted to this
gland a special Giga counter then
automatically traces an accurate picture
of the thyroid showing its size and
location and how fast it collects the
[Music]
iodine radioactive elements can also
heal phosphorus for example lodes in the
bones where its mild radiation can cure
certain blood
diseases the patient carries his
treatment with him even while he works
and sleeps
and then ractive Cobalt is used in the
famous Cobalt bomb but this bomb is a
friendly one one that is used in
hospitals for fighting that dread
disease
cancer and there is left to us the third
and Last Wish It is an important
choice many Legends tell of how wishers
made an unwise choice and how their Last
Wish destroyed the benefits of the first
two the atomic Genie weighs in his hands
the powers of both creation and
destruction as yet the world has reason
to fear those destructive
Powers so our last wish should simply be
for the atomic Genie to remain forever
our
friend we have inherited a wealth of
knowledge knowled from the great
thinkers of the
past that this Heritage would ever be
applied towards destruction was farest
from their minds and
hearts it lies in our own hands to make
wise use of the atomic
Treasures then the Magic Touch of the
genie will spread throughout the world
and he will crant the gifts of signs to
all mankind
[Music]
the great scientists before us gave us
knowledge of the atom and our last wish
will come true if we use the power of
this knowledge in their
Spirit then the atom will become truly
our friend
[Music]
now in Motion Picture theaters
everywhere you'll be able to see for the
first time Walt Disney's new Technicolor
feature Westward hold the wagons it's a
new and different outdoor drama telling
the exciting story of the covered wagon
families fighting their way west told
against a background of spectacular
Scenic Beauty in cinemascope and
Technicolor Westward H the wagons now
you and your family can see this
exciting Motion Picture entertainment in
a theater or Drive-In nearby look in
your newspaper for theater names and
show times this has been an ABC
television network film presentation